It’s crazy when you think about all of
the different kinds of foods we eat.
We just swallow and hope
it all works out for the best.
Well, as it turns out,
there are better ways to think about keeping
our bodies humming healthfully along.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
In this episode, Dr. Kristine Dennis takes
a deep dive into the research
around raising plant-based kids!
Dr. Dennis is our new
Senior Research Scientist
who also happens to
be a plant-based parent.
We start with a story about how
eating well-balanced plant-based diets
during pregnancy can reduce
risks of gestational diabetes
and hypertensive disorders
like preeclampsia.
Over the past two decades,
scientific and
professional nutrition,
and pediatric associations,
have issued official statements
and published position papers
about adopting vegan diets
during crucial life stages,
including pregnancy
and lactation,
infancy, and childhood.
While some of these associations
firmly agree
a well-designed vegan diet
can be healthy and support
normal growth and development,
others are more reserved,
and some caution against
vegan diets for children.
Those that are supportive
include the American
Dietetic Association,
which has held this position
for more than 25 years,
as well as
professional associations
in Australia, Canada,
Portugal, Italy,
the UK, Finland,
Germany, and Norway,
and Europe more broadly.
More reserved opinions
also came out of the UK
and Europe, including Spain,
and downright
dismissive positions
have come out of Slovenia,
Germany, Italy,
France, and Belgium.
What does the evidence say
about vegan diets in children?
Part of the challenge
starts at the very beginning,
with the exclusion
of pregnant people
from clinical trials in general.
With such compelling needs,
why are pregnant women
largely excluded
from clinical research?
Often due to ethical concerns,
dominated by fears
of fetal harm.
Even non-pregnant women
of reproductive age
often have to commit
to contraception
during the research period,
and those who become pregnant
must leave the study
with their data excluded.
That all adds up to a lack
of clinical trial data
on pregnant women.
Paradoxically,
these precautionary measures
may not have made pregnant moms
or their babies safer
because of the resulting
lack of evidence.
Some of the commentary
around vegan diets for children
includes this same concern
about the lack of data.
One researcher stated,
"In children we do not
have many good quality studies,
and the studies we do have come
mostly from vegetarian children,
and they are of
very varying quality."
But researchers are
attempting to fill this void,
starting with,
"To vegan or not to vegan
when pregnant, lactating,
or feeding young children."
The oldest
and largest association
of nutritional professionals
in the world,
the Academy
of Nutrition and Dietetics
considers a completely
plant-based diet
to be suitable during pregnancy,
lactation, infancy,
and childhood,
provided it is well-planned.
What exactly
does well-planned mean?
First of all, a diet
rich in a wide variety
of plant foods;
grains, legumes
(such as beans, lentils,
split peas, and chickpeas),
fruits and veggies,
nuts and seeds,
herbs and spices.
We want to limit vegetable fats
so they don't displace
more nutrient-dense foods,
and if you do use them,
choosing them carefully,
for example, avoiding
trans fats and tropical oils.
Also taking a DHA supplement,
consuming enough calcium,
and ensuring
sufficient vitamin D.
And most importantly,
not forgetting
about vitamin B12,
as Dr. Greger
has covered extensively
because it is so important
to ensure a regular
and reliable source
of vitamin B12.
Balanced plant-based diets
mean eating a wide
variety of plant foods
in order to sufficiently
meet energy requirements,
and paying attention
to some nutrients
that may be critical,
iodine included.
It's one nutrient that
should also be supplemented
during pregnancy
and breastfeeding.
What are the impacts
on the mother's health
of following a vegetarian diet
during pregnancy?
Gestational diabetes
affects around 14 percent
of pregnancies globally,
and even more
in some regions of the world.
It's also at the center
of the vicious cycle
of diabetes begetting diabetes.
Linked not only
to adverse pregnancy
and birth outcomes,
but greater long-term risk
of cardiometabolic disorders
for both moms and babies.
Research suggests
beneficial impacts
of plant-based diets
on blood sugar control.
What effect might that have
on risk of gestational diabetes?
A systematic review
and meta-analysis
on plant-based
dietary patterns
and gestational diabetes risk
found that those who ate
closer to a healthy,
plant-based diet
had a significantly lower risk
of developing
gestational diabetes.
Evidence from the
Harvard Nurses' Health Study II
suggests these benefits extend
to hypertensive disorders,
like preeclampsia,
with a 20 percent lower risk
among those eating
the most plant-based diets.
And this lower risk
could benefit moms' health
for years to come,
as hypertensive disorders
during pregnancy
are associated with
increased risk of stroke
later in life.
Note that Dr. Greger
previously covered
other pregnancy
outcomes, as well.
In our next story,
Dr. Kristine Dennis looks at the studies
on the IQs
of vegetarian children.
Many vegetarian parents believe
their children are brighter
than omnivorous kids,
but you don't really know
until you put it to the test.
And, indeed,
the IQ of vegetarian children
tested about 16 points
higher than average,
and their mental age exceeded
their chronological age
by about a year.
The researchers knew
the veg kids were bright,
but why were they
so much more superior?
There are obviously
confounding factors,
like maybe more highly
educated parents
are more likely to have
vegetarian children,
and they pass down both
their brains and their diets.
Even if there is
a cause-and-effect relationship
between vegetarianism and IQ,
were the children smarter
because they were vegetarians,
or did they become vegetarian
because they were so smart?
Researchers in the UK followed
8,000 kids for decades.
They measured their IQ
at age 10,
then came back 20 years later
and asked which of them had
become vegetarian during that time.
And, indeed, the smarter kids
had an increased likelihood
of being a vegetarian
as an adult.
The researchers even quoted
Benjamin Franklin,
saying that vegetarian
diets result in
"Greater clearness of head
and quicker comprehension."
According to the largest
and oldest association
of nutrition professionals
in the world,
strictly plant-based
diets are appropriate
for all stages of
the life cycle,
including childhood,
and may indeed
provide health benefits.
What about plant-based diets
and growth in children?
Some studies show that children
raised on restrictive
macrobiotic diets
suffer from growth stunting,
while others show
that those raised plant-based
may end up being
up to an inch (2.5 cm) taller.
In a systematic review
and meta-analysis
of children on vegan diets,
heights were lower in vegans,
but only because
they included a study
in which the vegan kids
were significantly younger,
mostly 10 to 14 years old,
compared to mostly
15 to 19 years old.
Once you remove the study
with the age disparity,
the height disparity
also disappears.
What about width disparity?
Population studies indicate
that vegetarian diets
are associated with
a lower prevalence of obesity
in both adults and children.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
As always, all proceeds from
book sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.